Guide to the George Edmund Haynes Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Edmund Haynes papers
1916-1972
1916-1950
JWJ MSS 101
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.94
(8 boxes)
The George Edmund Haynes Papers consist of correspondence, writings, and professional papers by and relating to George Edmund Haynes. Correspondence contains letters between Haynes and various professional groups that he worked for or with. Writings contain works by Haynes, including articles and book reviews; and a dissertation on Haynes by Daniel Perlman. Professional papers contain material relating to Haynes' professional work on various committees and boards, including the Federal Council of Churches, the World's Committee of YMCAs, the State University of New York Board of Trustees, and a survey of the work of the YMCA in South Africa.
Haynes, George Edmund, 1880-1960
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of George Edmund Haynes, 1953-1960 and Olyve Haynes, 1960-1972.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are also available on microfilm #1292. See folder labels for more information.
George Edmund Haynes (1880-1960)
George Edmund Haynes, American social worker, educator, and co-founder and first executive director of the National Urban League.
Scope and Contents
The George Edmund Haynes Papers consist of correspondence, writings, and professional papers by and relating to George Edmund Haynes. Correspondence contains letters between Haynes and various professional groups that he worked for or with. Writings contain works by Haynes, including articles and book reviews; and a dissertation on Haynes by Daniel Perlman. Professional papers contain material relating to Haynes' professional work on various committees and boards, including the Federal Council of Churches, the World's Committee of YMCAs, the State University of New York Board of Trustees, and a survey of the work of the YMCA in South Africa.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1916-1944. II. Writings, 1929-1950, 1972. III. Professional Papers, 1928-1949.
African Americans; African American sociologists; Sociology -- Research; Social work with African Americans; Sociologists -- United States -- 20th Century; Haynes, George Edmund, 1880-1960; Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America; State University of New York. Board of Trustees; World's Committee of Young Men's Christian Associations
- Correspondence, 1916-1944; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Correspondence with local and state interracial committees and various correspondence is filed at the end of the series.
  - Africa Consultative Committee of YMCAs, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Regards trip to Scandinavia
  - Federal Council of Churches, African Welfare Committee, 1937-1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Contains correspondence between Haynes and educational religious contacts for Africa
  - Fire Relief Project, Nashville, TN, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Also contains reports
  - Hampton Institute Study, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Also contains questionnaires
  - Harmon Awards, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Kellogg, Arthur P., 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Editor of The Survey
  - New York State University Temporary Commission, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Local and state interracial committees, 1925-1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Various correspondents, 1916 February-1918 February (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Writings, 1929-1950, 1972; Series II; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Contains writings by Haynes, including articles and book reviews. A dissertation on Haynes by Daniel Perlman is filed at the end of the series.
  - Writings by Haynes
    - "Africa, Continent of the Future," original typescript and typescript carbon drafts, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - "Negroes," article for the Social Work Year Book, typescript draft, corrected, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Various articles, original typescript and typescript carbon drafts, 1935-1944 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Book reviews, original typescript and typescript drafts, 1929-1940 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Stirring White Conscience: The Life of George Edmund Haynes" by Daniel Perlman, typescript (photocopy), 1972 June (Box 3, Folder 16-18)
    Dissertation in the Department of History, Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, New York University
- Professional Papers, 1928-1949; Series III; 1.47; (4 boxes)
  Contains papers relating to Haynes' professional work on various committees and boards.
  - Biographical and bibliographic information on Haynes, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
  - Commission on Race Relations, Survey Committee, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
    Minutes for meetings of October 1 and November 12
  - Federal Council of Churches, 1933 December 25-1946 October (Box 4, Folder 23-25)
  - Federal Council of Churches, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Federal Council of Churches, "Towards International Peace", 1940 (Box 5, Folder 27-28)
    Includes Carnegie-Murdal Study
  - International Survey of North American Christian Associations, 1928-1929 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - "Nova Scotia Tour", 1937 August (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Plenary Meeting of the World's Committee of YMCAs, report, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - "School of Race Relationship at Camp Kane", undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - State University of New York Board of Trustees, public hearings, 1948, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 33-34)
  - "Study Tour of Africa"
    In 1930, Haynes did a survey of the work of the YMCA in South Africa. In 1947 he conducted a similar study in other African nations. This work resulted in Haynes being chosen as consultant on Africa by the World Committee of YMCAs.
    - Correspondence
      - A-H, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 35)
      - I-M, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 36)
      - N-Z, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Interviews, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 38-39)
    - Governmental permits and letters of introduction, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - "Study Tour in Africa", typescript and handwritten draft, corrected, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 41-42)
    - Dinner given in honor of Dr. Haynes, invitations, letters of regret, and other correspondence, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Memos, notes, passports, etc., 1930 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence, memos, clippings, and other papers, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 45)